we're going to talk about your immune
system and how it can be enhanced to
fight viral infections welcome to True
Health Tuesdays so the first thing you
have to understand is that there are two
parts to your immune system and we're
going to talk about here the two parts
to your immune system there is the
innate immune system which as you can
see right
here and the Adaptive immune system now
the Adaptive immune system is is the
part of your immune system that
remembers previous infections we're
actually not going to talk about that
today that's the part of your immune
system that is related to getting
antibodies when you are infected with a
virus now what we're actually going to
talk today is about the innate immune
system the innate immune system is
programmed to be able to determine the
difference between self and a foreign
Invader without pre previous exposure
it's very important in terms of viruses
that you have never seen before and the
players you can see here outlined
specifically the monoy which is a cell
that eats things and of course the
natural killer cells which is also very
important one of the major components of
the innate immune system is something
called
interferon or I
FN
interferon is an
amazing product it's amazing product
that your body makes and it is designed
specifically to inhibit and to
prevent viral infections from taking
over your
body such to the point that if you want
to have a viral infection happen the
virus has to come up with a way of
getting around this system okay this is
like the major fence around a facility
if you want to break into this facility
you have to find a way to get through
this fence this interferon is the fence
that prevents viral infections and so
it's important that viruses come up with
a way to try to get around this let's
talk a little bit about that there's
been a number of studies that have
looked at this this is one that is from
2002 so over 20 GE ago we had some
information about this and here they
talk about viruses and interferon a
fight for Supremacy so in other words
viruses are trying to get into the human
body and interferon is one of those
special tools that your innate immune
system uses to prevent that from
happening let's read a little bit about
this from this paper that was published
in
nature they say here that type one
interferons are a group of antiviral
cyto kindes that are induced during
viral infections by viral replication
products such as double stranded RNA and
so this is a a trigger if you will if
this is present this is going to
trigger this type of an immune response
so these ifns or interferons exert their
biological functions by binding to
specific cell receptors this in turn
triggers the intracellular interferance
signaling pathway and you can see that
here later on this eventually induces
the expression of a large number of
interferon secreting genes so those are
IG
isgs as you can see here the workhorses
of the ifn
response they set up an antiviral anti-
prolif of and imuno Regulatory state in
the host cell however most if not all
viruses have it says here evolved a
broad spectrum of strategies to block
and interfere the ifn pathway in other
words again if the virus wants to be
successful it's got to figure out a way
to get around interferon common viral
strategies include blocking interferon
induction and expression intercepting
receptor binding of ifns through a viral
decoy um perturbation of intracellular
ifn signaling pathway and directly
downregulating the level expression of
these ifn stimulated genes so you can
see here okay so let's take a look here
and see specifically talking about coid
in this case what has been going on so
let's uh jump to now we're looking at
June 1st here in 2020 and they say here
that studies of SARS and Ms suggest that
interferon response is
delayed okay so these are successful
viruses that have been delayed compared
with Corona viruses that cause mild
disease with milder causes these two
Corona viruses that can cause severe
disease the patients with severe SARS or
Ms have higher viral loads and delayed
interferon
responses and they realized that even
back then for
SARS and for
Ms that patients
with more severe disease had less type 1
interferent activity in their blood and
we can see that here with SARS K2 notice
that if you look at interfer and
response here that those with mild
disease had higher interferon levels and
those with critical disease had lower
levels of
interferon so now enter this paper that
was just published this year in August
of
23 titled SARS kovy 2 Mac one is
required for interferon antagonism and
efficient virus replication in cell
culture and in
mice notice what they found here SARS K2
has a gene called Mac
one okay Mac one is a
gene that is producing a protein and
what they found is is that this specific
transcription product which is found
here in the gene around
orf1ab and uh specifically we're looking
right here on the gene that seems to
convey
resistance or at least some way of
preventing uh innate immunity from the
host in the form of interferon and let's
show you exactly what they found when
they did research on this what they
found was that when they used bronchial
cell
cultures and when they used alviola cell
cultures they found that compared to
Wild type SARS K2 virus when they put a
deletion in the Mac one gene notice what
happened there was higher levels across
the board in all of these in both the
bronchial cell cultures and also in the
Alvar cell cultures notice all of these
had higher levels of interferon when
they deleted that portion of the Mac 1
gene they also found in those situations
that the SARS K2 virus was able to be
cleared faster when they had higher
levels of of
interferon of course the question is is
could
interferon be a potential treatment in
the treatment of SARS kovy 2 here's a
paper that was published
recently in the New England Journal of
Medicine back in February of
2023 and it was a randomized control
trial looking at
subjects and in the subjects there was
83% of them which were vaccinated and
about 177% which were not and they
basically gave a single injection
subcutaneously of interfer on Lambda or
Placebo and they wanted to see whether
or not it would prevent hospitalization
or ER visits in people who had
outpatient Co 19 that presented within 7
days so again hospitalization or Ed
visits Within in 28 days of coming down
with SARS K2 and what they found was
that when they looked at the relative
risk in the placebo group 57 out of
108 had to go to be hospitalized or go
to the emergency room within 28 days
whereas those that were given interfer
on
Lambda uh in other words a way to boost
up in and increase interferon levels
notice that there was a reduction of
almost 50% now the absolute risk
reduction is simply the difference
between these two which was 2.9% which
translates into a number needed to treat
of 35 which is not bad the 35 number
needed to treat to prevent one
hospitalization or ER visit within 28
days that's pretty good now if we look
at the breakdown on this the question is
of course does this work for those that
are vaccinated and unvaccinated and the
answer is yes okay so remember that
83% of the subjects in this group had at
least one injection of a vaccine that's
how they counted vaccinated at least one
shot of a vaccine at any time in their
previous history so if we looked at
those 4.6% of those
people had to in the placebo group
become hospitalized or go to the
emergency room those that got pegal
interferon that dropped down to
2.4% okay whereas in the unvaccinated
arm there was
10.2% that needed to be hospitalized or
go to the emergency room in that group
whereas when they got uh the uh
interferon it dropped down to
4.2% so again a reduction in other words
there there was a reduction in both
groups
equally and uh this worked in other
words whether or not you were vaccinated
or
not and again let if we look at Co
hospitalization or death Co 19 you can
see here going from bbo
to the pegal interferon Lambda a
reduction whereas when they got this
single dose of a subcutaneous
injection you can see here that it went
from Placebo to pegal interferon there
was hardly any difference in terms of
Adverse
Events and so the results of this trial
showed that the risk of Co 19 related
hospitalization or an ed visit was
approximately 50% lower in the
interferon group than in the placebo
group results were consistent regardless
of vaccination status and the safety
showed that that U the incidence of
Adverse Events was similar in the two
groups of course we talked about this uh
earlier and that is that how important
it is that interferon be secreted and in
this randomized control trial we showed
here how giving exogenous or extra outof
body supplementation of interferon could
be beneficial the question is of course
is whether or not we could do this
Naturally by just telling the body to
produce more interferon and there's an
interesting study that was published a
number of years ago showing that
hypothermia so getting someone's
temperature up to 39° Centigrade could
do the same thing they say here 39°
centigrade in human volunteers by
immersion in warm water rapidly Alters
the cell populations in the peripheral
blood in addition to granulosis there is
an alteration in the normal ratios among
T lymy subsets now notice here that a
temperature threshold of 39° Centigrade
was able to produce tfold more
interferon than cells would drawn at
basil core body
temperatures and take a look at this
graphically so you can see here that
once it reached
39° there was a massive increase in the
amount of interferon and you may think
that this is actually new information
when in fact this is been going on for
some period of time and I draw your
attention here to the Battle Creek
sanitarium back in the 1900s where a lot
of this stuff was being pioneered by
luminaries in the field this was the
ability of increasing the body
temperature using a hot bath as you can
see here and by the way this is in the
same sanitarium this is a light therapy
which of course is very near and dear to
my heart because we've talked about
light therapy as well
here we can see bath attendance at the
Battle Creek sanitarium in 1890 and you
can see here that it obviously took a
lot of work to do this here we can see
more hydrotherapy being applied uh these
are hot towels that are being applied to
the human body to increase the core body
temperatures to induce um these sorts of
things of course they didn't know about
interferon at that time but they knew
that increasing the body temperature
seemed to have an effect on getting rid
of viral infections some of the famous
guests that would come to the Battle
Creek sanitarium people like Amelia
airheart the actor who played Tarzan in
the early series Sojourner Truth CW post
who of course in was the uh inventor of
post Cals along with of course the the
Battle Creek
sanitarium medical director who was John
harvy Kellogg but also
presidential people also came to the
Battle Creek sanitarian people like
Eleanor and Teddy Roosevelt Mary Todd
Lincoln Henry Ford for one George
Bernard Shaw and John D Rockefeller now
of course all of this was going on and
they were looking at this and of course
when the 1918 pandemic rolled around
there was obviously a a Thrust to see
whether or not this would work for that
as well and there was a gentleman by the
name of Wells rubel who was a physician
at the sanitary
u in the uh Northeast in Boston who saw
this as an opportunity to use this type
of hydrotherapy to increase the body
temperature and to have this effect I
don't think he knew that he was
increasing interferon at the time I
don't think they knew about that but he
said here and he published in this
journal article called life and health
which we'll put a link to in the in the
description here you can actually find
it on the internet as well he says that
the present epidemic mic of influenza
has furnished excellent opportunity to
test out the efficacy of rational
treatment in dealing with respiratory
disorders especially in conditions
accompanying and following attacks of
influenza here is what he showed he
showed that in the Army hospitals which
he compared his treatment to that early
on they did not use things that would
increase the temperature but rather
things that would decrease the
temperature things like aspirin which
had just come out in
1899 and notice that a whopping
16% of those that came down with illness
in the Army Camps went on to develop
pneumonia as opposed to only 2% in the
sanitariums who were given these
treatments to increase body temperature
and so they had very few pneumonia cases
once you develop pneumonia as you can
see there was a similar amount of people
who came down with death from pneumonia
actually even more in the sanitariums
but because so few developed pneumonia
you can see here that they enjoyed one
16th of the infection fatality rates
that the the Army hospitals did another
example that I can find looking back
because we don't have randomized control
trials on this is this the Danish
Norwegian Seminary the Hutchinson
seminary in Hutchinson Minnesota there
was an article that was published when
during the pandemic the the entire
Seminary came down with an illness very
quickly and we can see it here actually
published not in a scientific journal
but actually in a religious
periodical and it reported on what was
going on there in the Northwest in
Minnesota and it says here and I'll just
read blow it up here is on the authority
of Dr Fred Shepard Health officer of
Hutchinson City it may be stated that no
public institution in the state of
Minnesota up to date made a record in
handling influenza
the worldwide epidemic that has swept
Millions into their graves like that to
the credit of the Hutchinson 7th Day
Adventist Seminary it goes on to say
that the Seminary with 120 of its 180
students and teachers housed Under One
Roof was invaded by the melody 3 weeks
ago symptoms of the malady developed
with some 90 of these and under the
direction of Dr h lson a graduate
physician member of the Seminary faculty
every person showing indication of
sickness was at once put to bed with a
trained nurse taking the temperature and
watching for symptoms of the epidemic if
those symptoms develop the patient was
required to remain in bed there were no
so in other words there was isolation
here okay there were no drugs to be
given but with complete rest and quiet
when a carefully regulated end
fermentations now that's the term that
we use for putting hot
towels on the chest and it was applied
to the throat chest and the abdomen the
treatment is almost in every case reduce
the temperature of the patients in a day
or so and they were apparently well but
they did not end the matter with them
the next danger was the that of relapse
to guard against this every patient was
required to remain AB bed from to 5 days
after apparent full recovery according
to the state of their flu Affliction as
a result of this system of handling
disease that is scoring thousands of
victims every day there has not been one
case that could have been called serious
or a single death in the Seminary
although there were more than 90 persons
affected the record is remarkable it
makes the ordinary methods of dealing
with the flu appear irrational we will
add that we were indeed thankful to God
for his protecting care and for the
untiring efforts of Sister Louise kutson
our Seminary nurse and for the
assistance of the other nurses and
helpers notice here that it wasn't just
a matter of passing out meds this was
very labor intensive to do this kind of
work the hydrotherapy treatments under
the blessings of God are indeed helpful
as is recognized by this article so they
put a lot of emphasis here on the
hydrotherapy this just wasn't them doing
this this is also being studied and
researched around the world and there
was an Austrian psychiatrist by the name
of Julius Wagner yorg
who found in his observations that
patients in his asane Asylum who had
come down with neurosifilis seems to get
better seemed to get better when they
had a fever and so he had an
idea of actually infecting them on
purpose with the benign version of
malaria that would give high fevers that
was FX and fals aerium viac basically
and so when he infected these patients
with malaria they developed very high
fevers but notice that there were other
ways of doing this is a paper that was
published back in 2013 reviewing this he
would also use the immersion of an
individual in a hot bath or placing him
in a heat cabinet and it says here that
Wagner YX therapy was highly admired and
was used on neurosyphilis cases well
into the
1950s uh however with introduction of
penicillin in
1928 um fever therapy effectively ended
in other words they found a equally
effective way of treating this through
medications that was a lot less labor
intensive and actually as it turns out
um he won the Nobel Prize in medicine
you can see him right here actually
infecting a neuros syphilis case here
with the blood of somebody who was
infected with malaria and of course this
would the high heat and fevers would
cause the the induction of interferon
which would eventually kill the the
syphilis and for that he won the Nobel
Prize in medicine in 1927 for his work
showing that heat could actually treat
and cure disease and this is what he did
the work on in 1917 this is right before
the pandemic of
1918 in Austria he did this so we said
though that he won the Nobel Prize in
1927 in 1928 ironically very next year
there was the discovery of penicillin
and we have Alexander Fleming who
discovered these this medication and it
would kill bacteria on these Petri
dishes and for that he won the Nobel
Prize in 1945 for his the discovery that
was occurring in 1928 and this set us on
a completely different path this looked
at randomized control trials with
medications this was was much less labor
intensive and it was able to affect and
so what we did
here I want you to notice the paradigm
shift is instead of finding ways to
enhance the body's ability to to clear
the infection itself instead of finding
ways of enhancing the body's own
immunity what we started to do was do a
lot of the complicated work that the
immune system was doing and actually
find chemicals and products that would
affect the bacteria itself without
necessarily affecting the human body as
much as possible so these medications
otherwise known as antibiotics were
discovered which were much easier to
administer and so as you can see
remember now we had the bath attendance
very labor intensive but these
treatments were effective at inducing
interferons that would overcome the
infection of of the virus now a lot of
this work work from 1928 on involved
randomized controlled trials there
weren't a lot of randomized control
trials prior to that and so when this
type of treatment was at its Heyday they
didn't actually test this using
randomized Placebo control Trials of
course it'd be hard to do Placebo
control trials but it wasn't done and so
the issue here is that we do not have
very good randomized control trials
showing that this form of therapy works
however there was a time where it was
the standard of care and it was what
everyone did to improve outcomes in
viral infections and the reason why I
think this is important is because as we
talk about the pandemic and we look at
the pharmacological Supply chains and
how complicated they are how difficult
they are and how we could run out of
these things as we remember not only
this pandemic that we have just come
into and are still in some cases here
but we also think about future
pandemics uh let it not be forgotten
that it took us over a year to develop a
vaccine for this pandemic and so if
we're looking for a way to treat a viral
outbreak don't depend on a vaccine that
may or may not be already developed for
that virus similarly uh a lot of people
have argued that there are off label
already
manufactured uh medications that might
be beneficial against such a vaccine or
such such a viral outbreak that is not
taken for granted that may not be the
case there may or there may not be
something that is effective against
viruses at that point um however we can
say this that if there is something that
is effective there is a very good chance
that it's not going to be universally
available for a number of reasons number
one the supply chain is very fragile
number two there is a bottleneck in
terms of prescriptions and Pharmacists
and number three
is that if it is effective it will
likely be hoarded and taken for resale
just like toilet paper was and I think
that this is probably our best shot at
having something that we could
use if we could learn how to use this if
we could be uh intelligent in its use
for a potential outbreak in the future
and I'm not the only one that's thought
of this there is a gentleman by the name
of Bruce Thompson
who uh has also studied the protocols of
hydrotherapy going back to the John
Harvey Kellogg days and has put together
a beautiful website called Hydro for
coid this is also available on the
domain site traditional hydrotherapy
tocom where it goes through very
specifically how these things are to be
done and how they were done and I
believe it's a very actually uh Forward
Thinking website it's very specific it
says that this type of therapy Y is to
be used in addition to standard medical
care it's not to be used as an
alternative to standard medical care it
uses heat to enhances the body's ability
to fight off the Corona virus in the
early stages of infection I would say
that since this is stimulating your
body's ability to create uh interferon
that this not only works
for Co 19 but just about any viral
illness that would require interferon
and this I think is really important
they also go on and state here the how
fermentations are to be
used and for those of you that are
interested there is also the book
published by John Harvey Kellogg on
rational hybro therapy it's it was
published in 1918 ironically right when
the pandemic hit and it
was interestingly over a thousand pages
long so very complicated now there are
people that are looking at this and this
was published in medical hypotheses back
in 2021 hydrotherapy in prevention and
treatment of mild to moderate cases of
Co 19 again there has not been any
randomized control trials published on
this mode of therapy but there should be
I think that this is something that
should definitely be investigated it
could be done very easily and and its
investigation would be worthwhile so my
advice would be to learn how to do
hydrothermal therapy or hydrotherapy I
highly recommend going to the website
Hydro the number4
co.com and uh learn how to do this type
of therapy especially as we're entering
into the flu season and Co 19 is still
something that is there